Hi all good evening so how's your weekend going guys so give me thumbs up from audible
and visible thank you guys can anyone share the whatsapp group link
so how's your weekend going guys I have to log in in my system
how's weather at your respective places is it hot does it feel like summer already
we feel it completely different like why you know there's no winter in Hyderabad this year
must be our batch name was scale of instruction okay bangalore even bangalore okay then you
can say that if Bangalore is hot now Hyderabad is off to be I've been in Bangalore only for
three months and I have really great time there my voice is echoing okay let me recheck
is it better now guys can you if I speak okay still the same issue how many of you
feel that my voice is echoing not clear okay let me try to reconnect it
guys can you hear me again like I'm trying retrying it I rejoined the class
now okay is my voice is also good great great so okay there's a water issue in Bangalore
that's that's really crazy still still like we have much of summer is yet to be started because
I consider summer according to me is after Holi or Shivaratri specific to specifically
like isn't it that's how people say to us isn't it so let me share my screen let's test this one
also yeah someone is off the channel global warming you can see the my screen share right
guys is my screen share visible cool so let's have three minutes timer then we'll get started
I'll drop a message here and what's up
the message no cases is there any challenge with your assignments or like did anyone attempt
contests in practice mode the last vegetables is this one because I see there is a drop in
percentages of people who are trying to solve it I usually get the metrics of a bad so I'm
just thinking from your perspective like is everyone following up with their assignment
problems are everyone solving it okay I see less amount of people today in class is it because of
weekend Saturday class no idea okay something I'll come to that point yeah right the topics
we are discussing yes the problems that you get post class right those are the questions
that if you are able to solve could good enough okay he monkey has said that she's at school
it's such night okay notice okay after some revision will solve it okay the only reason
that I say that keep solving after each class is because the moment you will go for revision
right I'll be moving towards react I'll be moving towards node J's so it will be really difficult
to come back and catch it up that's the reason why I would suggest right after each class go
and try to solve it if you face any challenges to let me know because that's how you can keep
up in the right way or else it will be a burden for you at the last moment okay okay
let me set up iPad screen sharing
guys do let me know if you can see the screen share of iPad can you explain about the filtering
part we'll come to that coming so we'll come to that we'll cover it up everything so guys
let's get started I think we are high time isn't it can we get started a final thumbs up if you
can get started with today's class good so let's do this case till now this is the final class
for a can ban so we'll be completing all the features we discussed in the starting all features
then we'll go for deployment so two things that will be doing it okay now when it comes
to features we have already discussed like create a ticket or create a task delete a task
like change status of task and filter the task based on status so on top level these are the
four features right what we are trying to build in can ban would is it so we have addressed all
of this but first we'll try to recheck like if we have done this and we'll try to go through
each of this one use cases again revision of this one first we'll get started with this then
we'll come to something like storages in browser okay once we understand will implement one of one
of the storage that we use in browsers to our existing application and then we'll see what are
the advantages we get from out of that okay let's let's get started with the revision guys firstly
let's move to the code directly and launch the application so okay open here so firstly
going back again step by step for the each thing okay let's go here in the code now so for firstly
let me know if that create and delete part is clear now for everyone out of these four features
because create and delete is something that I have already explained more than two times or
three times while coding I have talked about it twice then why also explaining and revision
it in the last as I have done it multiple times so I'll talk about change of change status of a
task like how we are able to change the status and then filtering the task based on okay give
me a second I'll share the github link can anyone I'll pin that okay let me fetch it
this is a github order okay so guys let's let's go back and first let me create the
task let's say this is our task one I try to set the status of the pink then let's say also
I have a task to as a pink no once I do this so earlier we have done how we are creating it
how we are deleting it and how we are able to edit this particular thing right we have done all
of those use cases and we have implemented this one now let's see again revising the way we have
handled this change status like once you click on the top of this particular you know bar which
is pink in color like which is meant to be what we understood by that is the something a task
which need to be done or which is like not it started we haven't picked up to work on so once
you click on the top of the pink like it changes into green then to blue then to black this is a
status of a particular task right now how we have addressed this one is that if you see first and
foremost thing is we know that we have to have a event listener added to the each of the ticket
on the top of this bar again we went to the place where we were creating a ticket once we came to
this ticket we say that handle color function which is supposed to handle all the use cases so we went
into handle color and we had a ticket for each ticket we try to fetch this particular color band
okay like which is what I mean what I mean by color band is this is the color band okay once I get
this color band I added event listener to it okay click event listener then we have written the you
know statement that we have to do it like find the color of the band then the index of that color
from the colors array which is this colors array and then we need to update the color of a band
with the next color of the next index of the color let's say colors array okay this is what
we have understood it earlier so in order to find like the color which is like existing color we
have done iteration through the loop because we have discussed like while adding always new color
get added into the next next and next end status so there are basically two colors on the color
band two CSS classes specifically if you see it in the here right so what is like ticket color
which is dynamic in nature which will get light pink black and blue in the ticket color so while
iterating through the loop we were trying to find which is other than ticket color that is a current
color okay which is applied of the status then we were getting index out of the current color from
the colors array which is this one then once we got the index we were getting the new updated
index like which is an X color which where we have to move the status so once we have updated it to
handle the edge cases of rotational array or index out of bound we you know we use reminder in colors
of 10th which will put all the values between 0 to n minus 1 range or whenever you try to get
access from this particular array then we were removing existing color and adding new color so
this is something that we have handled it and I hope this is clear by now like how we did this
one guys is this clear give me thumbs up if you feel this is clear to you all I see one thumbs up
too cool anyone having any doubt anyone having any doubt on this part okay great but this logic
only works on the first ticket for me we'll check that on some bit we'll check like why where things
are failing I'll get back to you we can debug this in the like you know doubt sessions works
because I'm able to show you right different colors it's having currently okay we'll check
that now next thing next thing what we have seen is like like on selection of this one let's say
now you have the different tasks being created with a different statuses what if you want to
filter the task based on the colors like all that like the status so when I click on a green if you
see okay let me see this why is this breaking did I miss this up
or did I do any change here let me reset this code
okay
don't save let's recreate the task task hyphen one pink color then let's say you have task
hyphen two green in color okay once you have this we should be able to filter this one like
pink and with green or like whenever you click double click you should be able to render all
the tasks depending on whichever thing you click it now how did we address this one was like firstly
again writing a event listener from point of view like because user is clicking somewhere so we
should be able to figure out where user is clicking and how we should be able to add a
listener to this one so if you see from the elements perspective right and I select this
one all these four particular depths which are rendering color there's a common class called as
color so we can do query selector all with this particular color class and fetch all the four
different colors right same thing we have done here in the code that we were trying to fetch the
colors okay query selector all and on this each of this color we were adding an event listener
of click once we added event listener then we from from that click event we were able to find
which color user is selecting this was we were able to do it this one because when you see in
this let's say if user is clicking this one from the class list 0th index belongs to light pink
light green light blue and black so using the first index like 0th index from the class list
we are able to find the current I mean filter that you are clicking user is clicking on once
we get this color we were filtering the existing tickets available from the ticket array where
we stored all the tickets right once we have the filter tickets which is again having an area of
filtered different tasks now then we went on to remove all the tickets existing in the screen
like whatever tickets are there using quick ticket container if you say what is this ticket
container go back and if you see here in the main main card ticket container all the tickets
are basically having a class of ticket content we are selecting all tickets and then trying to
remove all of them which are existing in their dog like on the screen then we are recreating
all the tickets which using the filtered array this was something that we have done in the last
class so I hope this part is clear guys like how this filter is working anyone having still
any doubt on this one if anyone is having doubt they can give me thumbs up they can
state their point I can repeat it no issues because as far as considering the development
mostly we have covered the development part today it will be like you know talking about
some storages and deployment that's it if you have doubts I can repeat it okay great so if
this point is clear I want to show you one of the bug okay now if you see in the console right this
was an array which is having a ticket information now if you see the ticket info says task one now
what if I go and update this ticket information as task zero one okay and I close this one do
you see whether this particular thing is getting updated like this particular array information
where we're storing all the tickets this is not getting updated right so this was the one point
that we missed in the last class that's something that we have to address it so I'll show you the
code just think of it where we can how we can deal with this one let me open that code where
we were adding this one yeah this is the handle lock now if you see it here we were handling the
lock and we were making that container as a editable but here we have to update this
particular ticket right whichever thing is being edited now you can you guys think for one two
minutes and what we can do it here what approach we can follow here use the code base that you
have with you like the github share if you need a reference to go up and move up and down okay go
to this file in the Kanban board script.js just think for a one two minutes if you can come up
with any point or anything that you can address it because on editing each ticket we are not
updating this array it's just that we have to update this array
meanwhile I'll change some code here if anyone are trying to think it please do think it
meanwhile I'll update some changes here let's say I write down on the top say return
ticket array dot find index inside this will get each time I get a new ticket and I have to check
something where ticket ID is equal to ticket ID so we can update the unique ID of a ticket that
is updated and update the content and yeah that's a straightforward thing right Thiraj
thanks for pointing it down so first thing guys I'll come to that point as Thiraj suggested if
you see this is the same code as this one just I've used a find index point like a method a library
method which is provided on arrays like you're trying to find an index where this condition is
meeting like getting the ticket based on the ticket ID I mean from the ticket array whole
tickets array where we are storing all the tickets so I'll remove this part of code just
instead of iterating and doing with this condition now firstly in order to find which ticket we are
doing here we don't have identifier which we have to update it so if we need something here is
ticket ID so let's get that ticket ID first like which ticket we can update it okay I go back here
and they go back here this is handle lock so let me pass here ticket ID so here we have ticket ID
so I'm passing it down once I have ticket ID what I can do it here is that let's say firstly
let's let's get the index okay ticket index from ticket array where we are storing all the tickets
right how we can do this same condition again find instead of like find index and writing this
down I'll use this reusable method just we have below it's a get ticket let's say this is something
that we have and I can pass ticket ID okay once we give this ticket ID we will be getting the
exact ticket we need it okay and let's say I once we have this inside this let's say we'll have a
ticket index inside this one right so out of this object what we'll do is that inside this ticket
array we'll try to get that particular ticket dot whatever we have ticket ticket dot ticket ID get
me that index out of that ticket array then we will be updating the particular task right if you
remember the variable that we were storing while creating it if you go on to top ticket info right
let me get this as a ticket info and we'll update with the content whatever content is there now in
order to get the content also like you can do something here is that ticket task area dot value
isn't it or so what I'm trying to do it here is that just updating the content let's see if this
is working firstly and I don't need this as a let let's make it as a const trying to get the
ticket from the you know using the ticket ID once I get the ticket out of that I'm getting ticket
ID and trying to update the information now let's see if I create something okay ticket
has been already declared let's say what I can say yeah it's a task to be updated
okay now let's see if this is fine yeah now let's create one task saying some gibberish
and let's say I have this okay cannot set property of undefined this thing happened
because something we have done at the position this has failed create ticket 110 handle lock
okay inside this handle lock it got failed now why did I get failed okay so this is trying to
update each time so let's let's cut this word and and we have to do it only when country data
right only when we are trying to edit it or else we can say let's put it here itself but
adding the edge case now the edge case would be only if you are able to get the ticket then do
this one let's see if this is working fine yeah now what I'm trying to do it here is that once
let's say if you have you see go and see the existing ticket I have something serious already
something is written there let me try to update this as a task one okay and let me try to close
this one it didn't execute it but let's say if it is coming inside this part of code let's say I
try to update it again let's see I have this ticket ID and when I say this let's say if
we have something meeting this condition now this is never getting true let's fix this one how can
we do this no okay instead of writing it here only when we are making it as a false when we
are stopping edit right then we can update the content of it let's say if this is working as
expected now once I click here like an edit button and let's say I try to update content
as task hyphen one then once I click this no once I get this task I got 0th index okay first and
foremost thing is that instead of getting a ticket here we are actually getting the index
out of it let me reverse this code give me a second guys or it will break the multiple use
cases yeah whatever I have done let me re-paste this one then it will work
let me remove this let me play this one update this as a task hyphen one and then close it up
once I try to close it up I'm going here then let's say I come to this statement return
statement so I'm getting the ticket information which need to be getting updated and once this
is returned I'll get the ticket here so I'll have a ticket ID okay so I'm having the ticket
ID but not index so I supposed to find index here okay so the method that I was using was
altogether I have to find here from the ticket array using this ticket ID ticket array dot
find index let's say I have ticket inside this ticket I'll get ticket ID dot let's say I have
ticket ID here once I have this I can use directly then update it pardon me guys I'm
trying to confuse you all the one final check let me check this task hyphen one then let me
try to close this button once I have now I have the index as a minus one that's great
hmm why this is happening okay there is nothing as ID here ticket ID is supposed to be this one
so let me do the final check task hyphen one and then let's click close button once we are here
let's hopefully this time it gets the right thing now I got the zeroth index that's great
and I'm trying to get the exact info but when I get this I'm getting as a undefined now ticket
task area let's say I say that ticket task area inside that dot value okay I don't have this one
let me check inner text okay inner text is something that I should be using it for the
text area field this is not a form field form group field so I have to update this way so I
hope you understand how debugging really helps like if you see the way I'm trying to fix the
issues or try to find the you know use cases let's say now I go back here in the console I
have task one I once I close this I'm supposed to update it as a zero one no it is updated here it
is not printing it because the cons yeah it is updated as a task zero one so this was a one of
the edge case that we were missing in the last class I hope this point is clear how this is
working guys guys did I confuse you doing all this stuff parallelly or is it clear
because I was debugging it parallelly I was speaking on that one guys is anyone able to
follow up or give a thumbs down if you didn't understand it it's pretty cool right I can
jump on to it and we explain the things okay great one thumbs down guys let's keep this
interactive okay yeah sure I'm coming back to this code so this the main issue was that we
were not able to you know update the current when we are updating the content we are not
updating this an array memory array that we were using it right this particular ticket array so
what I did is that once user is you know clicking on edit once user is clicking on edit like edit
button and updating the content then locking that particular ticket when user is locking
the ticket I come into this part where user is locking it I go and pick it up the current
ticket index like from the ticket array where all the tickets are stored using this ticket ID
whichever is passed into handle lock using that ID I try to find which particular ticket is where
it is stored the existing ticket which are trying to edit it once I find the index out of it then
I'm going inside the ticket array fetching that particular object of ticket then I'm getting
the ticket info and updating with the existing whichever user has updated the content and how
I'm able to get this because here itself we got the access to this attribute and we were
actually updating the whether it is content available or contained in a true or false condition
now is are you able to relate this one I see only one two three okay great guys so I hope all the
logical paths right from the features of the project those points are clear isn't it like
because we have handled four use cases now if you see handle remove handle lock handle color
the handle color is changing the status now even here even here even here the thing that we have
missed is we have to update this one also isn't it we have to update this one also color when color
status is changing we are still not updating here let's say if I click on a green light
pick is not converted into light green here so we have to update this particular thing also let's
fix this up same thing same thing I'll go on to the top where I'm passing I'll pass the ticket ID
here same thing once I pass a ticket ID I'll go below in the handle color let's say I have
ticket ID once I have ticket ID let's say you're going to handle lock I'll fetch this particular
thing okay and I'll keep it here okay I'll keep here and it should be instead of ticket info I'll
say say it as ticket color because ticket color is something the object that we are trying to
update it and instead of ticket task area dot inner text which is now we don't have here but
something that we have to update it as new color right whichever user is changing it to new color
now let's see if this is affecting here firstly I'll go and create some random task and I'll
create options button once I have this let's say cool if I if I go and check in the console
okay ticket is not printed let's say I edit this task as a task one once I am able to edit it let's
say I try to print the ticket array itself here nothing is printing ticket array okay this is
we are having it 0th index now this sdcd is whatever it is it should be updated with task
FN 1 once this is done okay let me reprint this one ticket array then yeah it is updated as task
FN 1 now let's change the color from light pink to light green now once it is changed let me see
if it is in memory updated or not yeah it is updated as a light green I hope this this is
also clear right same lines I copied but I'm updating the ticket color inside that object
whichever particular ticket I'm selected so we have handled all the use cases edge cases for this
one so I hope this code point is clear like how we are doing handling it what I'll do is
that I'll give a commit as a code completion features completion okay now let's let's do
so guys I have you know modified some of the CSS and things I have stashed the code I will try
to show you what I have done okay let me see this okay I have some made changes I'll show
you those changes now if you see here the changes have done here is that I have added added a new
header okay from the existing changes I'm just trying to teach you because these are something
that doesn't really take time to explain so if you see between this text right light pink light
green light blue black I've added content like to be done in progress validated and completed and
also I've added a new div under this colors like you know having a header as a Kanban board and
added one image from the particular website okay which keeps a Kanban to do list side of thing one
then again going back to the colors wherever you have colors have added the content to verify so
that we know it by the whenever you add it in resume you need to know like what when you select
particular color what you are exactly doing it okay so I hope this this changes are fine right
easily understandable whatever changes I made in HTML okay then going back to CSS if you see
right let me go back to the CSS part I've just added for whatever header I've created same
display properties and for the image whatever image I added in the header I've added some
height and width same I've manipulated some height and widths nothing much more interesting
things now let's see once how does our project look once we loaded it now if you see it here
well how what changes I made I have made it every box as a rounded edge to be done in progress and
validate and completed then I've manipulated the CSS also now let's say you create a task one and
say that here task needs to be done and you click this one tickets also how these are getting
created I've moved from the center to the start now let's see if I create another task task hyphen
2 and let's say this task is already in progress I want to keep it in progress now this is talking
about progress let's say if I want to filter it which are the tasks which need to be started on
you can always check that to be done or else if you want to check which task is in progress
the by wording you will be able to find us and when user clicks double click you will all be you
will be able to again reload back okay again still all those functionalities will be still working
like if you want to delete it you can still delete it okay so does this look better guys
after some CSS changes and things that I try to play around with cool so let me push this code
also let me push this code to okay now cool let's get back on to the browser
and let's create one task let's create one simple task as a task on itself now comes
the one of the feature that is the last feature that we have to work on once I create a task
and if I let's say if I close this browser or if I refresh this page we are not able to
persist this task isn't it the task are gone because all the tasks that are trying to store
is real-time memory which is like when the script file is loaded and this script file is always
loaded as a new file whenever your HTML file is loaded isn't it once you load HTML this script
file is loaded and each time the script file is loaded if you see on the top itself we are
creating an empty ticket array you know so all the time whenever we are not able to store this
data anywhere so now we'll try and find out what are the possible you know abilities of features
that browser provides or where we can store these tickets or what we can do around around
these things okay now let's go to iPad no I will talk about bit storages okay no why firstly why
we do need storages let's talk on that part actually storages in browser first thing if
you remember all the websites right you go for Facebook or Instagram or any of the websites
YouTube your scalar right scalar website or something you might be also using a sleep code
right each time you go to the sites you need not to log in like once you log in there somehow it
remembers your username and password and whenever you try to log like load it to your website you
are automatically logging back into the system isn't it have you seen that use case right now
how this is possible how this is possible any any idea guess how this is working that once you
log in into an application you need not to log in again and again so just think of in a
way where your username and passwords are stored like once you enter somehow your browser remembers
your credentials or the okay so one of the suggestions I got is cookies any other ideas
case browser cache it how many of you have got through this keywords browser cache and cookies
how many of you heard this one in your life I hope everyone have heard this keywords right
okay great now I'll talk about few things here from storage perspective right so this all the
development in web its perspective web it happened before HTML 5 after HTML 5 okay now
this cookies whatever cookies are there now this cookies were used before HTML 5 and this
was our data storage our data storage was provided by browser and accessible you can
always access on document API okay on document API you will always able to access the cookies
now let's see if I go on to my browser and I try to load scaler.com let it load now
once I open the inspect tool parallelly it's working too slow my voice and internet is fine
right you are able to hear me out now I am not sure why scaler is loading so slow
okay my system started working slow
okay give me a second yeah it's lagging a bit right
okay I'll rejoin the class give me a second I'll rejoin the class now this looks this looks better
is it okay I'll rejoin the class give me a second I'll try to load it again once this is working fine
once I rejoin it okay it's not working I think I have to restart the browser yeah give me a
second yes I'll rejoin it
okay I'm not able to cut the call even cut the class call
okay let me rejoin it
guys rechecking sorry for disturbance am I audible and visible now
okay great let me try to reshare the screen okay let's do this
I think I didn't restart my system from long that's an issue but do let me know if you can
see the screen share good no let's try to load scaler.com yeah thank God it's loading
it's loading quite fast now so coming back to the console now let's see there are too many things
are happening but I was talking about talking about cookies now as I say that cookies will be
part of document API let's say if you say document dot okay okay you will be able to print all the
cookies that you are actually you know actually a scaler is using no cookies are the one of the
solution that was earlier used okay earlier used before HTML5 was introduced as one of the storage
capacity okay this cookies if you see they have already you know converted this cookies into a
different language or they have you know what you can say mask this data with different things like
encryption format so you might be seeing like a different visitors and everything but now let's
say if I go back into that application if you see if I go back into applications and I go into cookies
part let's say if I go into cookies part and let's say if I clear this cookies but if I let's say
if I clear all the cookies if you see here whatever my if you see my name is here you can see right I
have logged in as a thumb now if I refresh it you see I got logged out so it what what we can infer
from here is that at least this cookies is storing some information about my user details isn't it
username and password or authentication details can we say that so cookies were used before
HTML5 but still they are used till today's date where you store user info and you can
have personalization data like the if you see I have something like a mentee access
instructor access so this thing will be also present inside this here itself in the cookies
now why this cookies comes into the rule is like earlier if you want to share information right
let's say this is a client and this is a server whenever there is an exchange of resources happening
yeah it's storing inside the browser somewhere so whenever there's an exchange of information
is having whenever you send a request and response to the server each time you send a request to the
server server should be able to identify that hey this particular user is trying to get the resource
resource right now in order to identify for each API call you make you are supposed to send user
information along with that credentials which can be identified on the server okay so once
user locks in what this do is once the user you know login into any website this particular
website they what they do is the store credentials store credentials inside cookies and each time
you make an API request each time you make an API request to the server they always also share
credit credentials in the request to the server so that server can authenticate and give back
the response and user need not to log in each time each time he is trying to interact with the
server I are you able to follow up guys yeah okay let me try to re-explain this logic what I was
talking about now what I was saying is that earlier I've just shown you in from the scaler
website where once I cleared the cookies you know I got locked off automatically so we can
infer from that particular perspective is that you know we are storing something like user
information user personalization information okay okay so in a same way for how these cookies
are used even in today's date is that like you have two things client and server once you have
this client and server like let's say I'm trying to getting into interact with some other servers
which are present in the back end now each time I go and try to get me get information I'll say
that hey can you give me this information to this meeting or this data or anything I have to
authenticate right I have to say that I'm a genuine person I have access to your content
can you give me this credit this information so each time once user logs in what in what we
does in website is that you know like we store user credentials in like cookie and each and
every time whenever you make a request to the server you also send this cookies in the request
object to the server and server will parse that authenticate whether the request is valid okay
once only we find that this request is valid only then it sends back the response is this clear
guys what I'm trying to explain here what cookies does okay so cookies were used in real time only
nowadays only when you're trying to communicate between two systems this is all cool but now
cookies have a limitations cookies have a limitation with respect to size you cannot
store GBs of amount of data in it so only 4 KB amount of data that you can store 4 kilobytes
of data okay only 4 kilobytes of data that you can store in it and this thing will be in terms
of a string data type like if you see whatever I printed here earlier okay whatever I printed
in the console let's say even if you try to get the cookie now let me try to clean this up and log
in okay now I just got logged in into this one let me do this
okay
now once I log in back and I show you that you know document.cookie and guys is my screen lagging
again like I see there is too much slowness let me see my internet connection
okay it's fine right now if you see each time right each time you make a request
each time you make any API calls right let me explore this one
now let's say you are trying to fetch this one whenever you are trying to make a request
right you will be sending all the cookies along with it like in each in request headers there
is something called as request headers let me see this one expand this one
inside the request URL itself they are appending it okay now if you go and try to compare this one
right all these things let's say if I copy and paste it and in console you will be able to see
all these parameters right here somewhere kept so you'll see you what I generally meant to say is
that whatever details are there here all those details are being generally sent over each API
call to the server to identify and you know get the access for us from the server and get the data
back okay this is what cookie does on top level is this clear what cookies does what's the role
of cookies in real time and this cookies comes with another another use case which is like having
expiry date now if you see if I try to minimize this one each cookie will have its expiry date
you can always when when you are setting up the cookie right you can always give it like what is
expiry date if you go and say the console and try to find here expiry date okay they
haven't introduced here expiry date okay but only when user is logging out the cookies are
getting clean but there is no expiry date for this one as of now okay now if this point is clear
I'll come to the other parts what happened in the history of web development after HTML5 was
introduced okay so after HTML5 it got introduced in web there were two other sort of browsers those
came into the role one thing is called as local storage the other one is called a session storage
now how many of you have heard this two words I think something session storage is something
like really like day-to-day used word isn't it okay now these two words let's explore this what
are the common things that this helps us and how they are really helpful okay now first and
foremost thing since these are acting as a databases or a storages on the client side
now what first use case they did it is that in browser level they added more space let's
say I write down some differences space amount of data that you can store when it come to local
storage they say that you can add a 10 MB of data and when it comes to session storage they say that
5 MB of data can be stored 5 MB okay now this one what they say is that if you want if you want
let's say if you go if you go if you see this if I go back on a scalar and what if I close if I
close this and I reopen this scalar academy right still I have locked into it right now but if you
want to clean up once the user is closing that app once user is closing the tab or going to the
next tab if you're if user is doing that thing if you want a particular you know user to be
logged out then you can use something called a session storage what do I exactly mean is
that let me write down the sentence that it will be able you will be able to understand this one
like let's say expiration date
okay as soon as browser is closed or tab is closed so what do we exactly mean is
that once a user is closing the browser or the tab right in which website is loading if you are
closing that by any chance all this 5 MB free space will be freed up okay and this is not
particular one for you know but these are particular for websites okay and for when
comes to local storage there is no expiration date until unless user manually clears it
clears the memory is this clear guys like what is a basic difference like between local storage
and session storage related to expiration date session storage is like something related to
particular session and how do you define a session until unless user is logging out from the website
closing that app or closing the browser itself once you user closes the particular website or
thing it means that session for that particular use case is completed once that session is closed
this memory will be freed up and when it comes to local storage it like until unless you go user
goes and particularly clean it up this memory will be there all the time okay guys is this clear a
basic difference between local storage and session storage I got only one thumbs up I have good
amount of people in class I just need few more if there is anyone who don't are not able to
follow up difference between cookie local storage and session storage okay this was
used for communication between networks okay and only 4 KB of size and so they were storing string
format content okay and like you know this like both on client side and server side you'll have
and this cookie is provided by browser under the document API when it comes to local storage this
was used in HTML 5 once HTML 5 was introduced to store like this is an actual DB on a client
side where it acts like a database until unless you manually clears it the data will be there
okay 10 MB of data that you can store and this is a persistent data source until unless user clears it
memory no when it comes to session storage 5 MB of data and when whenever user is closing the
tab or you know ending the like closing the browser so you know this this memory will be
freed up and reset it okay those points so I hope the top level basic difference is clear now
according to our project use case just let me know what could be the type of storage that we
want to use what type of storage that we want to use local storage any any any suggestions guys
why do you think local storage why not cookies or any other thing
firstly we have tickets and the tickets are the objects in size and they can go the content
can be greater and we might need more amount of space and we want those tickets to be persistent
those tickets to be you know persistent like they stay in the browser with us okay not that
once we close the tab that all the tasks are gone isn't it so we don't have user credentials
because we don't have login details we don't have server we need to authenticate so cookies
is out of picture session storage we don't need it because that's use case is completely different
we are not building something like a bank website where once user clicks a close on a tab
or closing a browser we want to erase all the data isn't it so clearing like using local storage
where user manually deletes or you know play around with the local storage directly that
gives us more user control as some bits is so I hope everyone agreeing with point like why we
are actually choosing local storage over the other things that point should be clear which
one to use in which use case okay now let's say I try to discard this change as of now no
so for interacting with local storage right let's go back to the browser okay my browser is here
okay by default we if you want to access a local storage right you have three methods let's say
if I go and type down local storage dot set item okay whenever you are trying to add it you can
always set it now in while you're setting it up this function takes two things key and value now
inside the key let's say I say that my username okay and inside value I can always pass on any
string it should be string objects needs to be serialized when you're trying to store it inside
the local storage now once I click enter here let's see once I click enter and I go into this
application storage and I open the local storage okay so if you see here my username is got stored
inside this database inside the key value pair this looks like a no SQL database okay at runtime
but doesn't have so many features as you have it in no SQL okay now if you want to get any
information right if you want to get any information out of this local storage you have to use get item
and you have to pass on the key this works like a hash map where you see in a hash map you store
this was a hash map of string comma string general use cases like that once I do this local sure to
get item I'm able to access whatever value is set and if I want to clean up I can say
local storage dot remove item okay and I can pass on the key my username once I do this if I go
back inside the application if you see there is no key present here so one way of doing this one
is like let's say one way of doing this one is like doing it using code the other way around is
let's say that you once you set this item the other way of clearing this one is like you go
back here you manually clear it up you manually clear it up using this key okay and there's
the other way around like you can go and say that empty the cache and hard reload once you
do empty a cache and hard reload you are trying to remove the cache which is present inside the
browser so I hope these points are clear like how can you set it get the like local storage
item and how can you remove the item then there is another thing another method that is used which
is clear once you clear it right you manually are doing same thing which is like clear the
cache and hard reload okay the clearing the whole local storage from the code okay if this thing is
clear can we go and implement this logic case in our code can we do this let's let's do this
guys let's implement this one let's go step-by-step firstly we'll go to create ticket let's go to
create ticket wherever ticket is being created now when this ticket is being created when this
ticket is being created one thing we have to do how is what we have to do is like let's say local
storage dot set item setting the item and we can say that what type of let's say we say that a task
okay I can say all the tasks and since it stores only strings as I have told you what I'll do is
that I'll do JSON dot stringify to convert an array into string object okay then I'll pass inside
that ticket array once I do this once I do this okay let's see if we are able to store all the
tasks that we are creating inside this local storage this way going back to browser loading
launch our website again let's say once we have this I go to inspect okay let me have application
open parallely inside the local storage if you see currently whenever I launched it there was
already a ticket task present okay let me clean this manually firstly and let's create a task
step-by-step okay now I'll say that a task one and I say to be done and once I click this let
me remove this debugger and let's go back to application storage now if you see inside this
task one got stored okay now let's create another task as a task two now if I refresh
if I refresh do you think still like we have information stored okay that's fine we have two
tickets we are able to store this data but what if if I refresh the script will be automatically
loaded and be running from top to down isn't it the script will be loaded from top to down
now in order to address that issue right in order to address that issue or in the use case that when
whenever we close the tab and reopen the tab what I have to do is that each time this ticket get you
know created a ticket array empty I have to do one condition is that I'll check in this as a
local storage get items and I'll see that if there are tasks already what was the exact key
plural task okay if there are already present tasks in local storage if there are tasks hey do
one thing get this ticket array update this ticket array by getting this information how
can you do this let's say local storage again dot get item of task but the trick here is
that since since it will give is give us like instinct format I'll have to pass this code I
have to pass this code convert this into array isn't it whatever the string is there I have to
pass that to convert back into an array and upgrade this ticket array once this ticket
array is updated I have to recreate all the tickets which are present inside inside ticket
let's say I have each ticket now for creating each ticket we were using earlier create ticket
inside this create ticket we were passing three informations earlier if you see if I
find create ticket okay this information isn't it let's copy this and paste it here
so so is this clear guys what I was trying to do it here I'm just updating this array with
the existing information and also trying to recreate them onto the page let's see if this
is working fine as of now now if you see we have two tickets inside this memory anyways it won't
be deleted once it is stored that we know it right even if I refresh it okay it's it's I see
that I'm getting the error assignment to a constant variable let me recheck okay this is
how I have to make it as let okay now going back into the application still I have in memory two
tickets are there task 1 and task 2 if I refresh it I still see one error cannot access create
ticket okay let's let's do one thing since we have used constant variable though the hosting
works hosting works in a different way right we have that those are throwing error because
of ES6 syntaxes now once I had do here add create ticket on top and once I click play now
let's say this task 1 got created but let's see in the application we have two tickets only task
1 got created cannot access handle remove before initialization okay so let me do one thing I have
to move all the methods on to the top also this method
okay now let's see if this is working fine now do you see this ticket task 1 and task 2 got
created automatically I didn't do anything I just refreshed the browser now now let's say if we
create if I even if I close this let's say for even if I close this even if I close this and I
reload it let's say I clean this I reload it once I load this and I click play now if you see the
task 1 task 2 got created automatically because in memory this task was present is this clear
guys how local storage is helping us now now these are use cases completely handled is our
use cases completely handled do you think we have still use cases that we have to handle here
adding part is done we have to handle remove also isn't it whenever user is deleting a ticket we
have to update the local shortage also right so let's go to that part let's go to that part where
we go for removing that items okay now if I go and check for the remove we are already slicing
you know if we are already splicing the ticket array so what if instead of using a remove item
I go to local storage let's say I try to find local storage I just do this thing again there
let's say I do this again so why I'm doing this again is that because ticket array is being
updated here ticket array got updated when we removed one item from it again I'm updating this
local storage with the updated array simple you are able to understand this point right why I'm
writing it this way again instead of using remove item okay so I hope this point is clear now once
I let's say once we go check this let's say if I go and click the delete once delete button is
activated if you see here we have two tasks 0th and first index bottom let me minimize this one
okay and I go and click on this task to if you see the 0th task task one got deleted here okay
so that's how we are handling remove part also no do you still think that every use case is
handled think of this guys if is all use cases handled update is left isn't it no what if I
copy this content again go to handle log and update it here itself because again if you see
ticket array is getting kept in sync again so ticket array is having updated information I'm
just updating the local storage using set same thought process okay that's the reason why I have
everywhere I'm using set item that's the reason why earlier I for it first time itself I've taught
you that how all the methods you can use it what are the what are the all methods that you can
leverage it okay now let's say if we want to convert this into task one once I create into
task one and I close this back you see here this also got updated as task one let's say if I go
and update as a task zero one and I update this one this has been updated as task zero one you
find this good guys like everything is stored in your database on each click it is getting
updated in your database local database right and imagine if I deploy and give it to you you can
actually use as a to-do task for to-do list for yourself in day-to-day life can man more you can
keep on adding more features I thought like if you're going to add this in your resume I should
make it bit more look neat and tidy that's the reason why I try to make it everything rounded
I didn't play it on one use case which is this ticket one you can make this ticket look really
beautiful depending on the your wish like how you want to do it I would be really happy if anyone
want to you know play around with this one because tomorrow is Sunday if I even receive one PR I would
be really happy with that would anyone would be interested contributing this one like make it
look beautiful add it into your resume because we'll deploy this what you can do is like you can
always add a bookmark like I have a bookmark you can always bookmark as a Kanban board you can
maintain your to-do list in your browser that you have built it so you will say that hey this is
application built by me and I'm using it it would feel good that you are building something and you
know the real-time production bucks you've won't fix it whatever features you want to add it okay
now yeah I'll talk about how to deploy but all the logic still now I hope everything is clear
everything is clear right no what I'll do is that
guys can I remove this file because I want to when I go for deploy I don't need this
script file to be present here so I'll delete this file anyways I have taught you like how
can you handle that even bubbling okay yeah we can host this I'll talk about that so let's say
I push this code as a code completion get commit minus nm code Kanban board
now I have one assignment guys one feature one thing that I want to give it to you is that let's
say you go back tomorrow if some if you try to implement that's all good or else if you want me
to implement I'll do that it as a offline because it's a homework for us all of us okay just I'll
tell you what you can do it is that if you see here we are able to filter the task based on a
status isn't it we are able to filter based on a status but what if we want to filter based on the
task content if you go into any e-commerce site right you go into e-commerce site you have a
search bar right always search bar right this thing just think of it how can you implement it
let's just like let's write down the lines right let's say if I try to write down what we can do
it here if you want to implement this let's say this is an extra add-on feature
okay what you can do it is that you keep a like let's say key up key up event okay when I say
key up event whenever user is typing it down when user leaves that key listener will be
listener will listen right now whenever user types down anything you go pick this
ticket array okay filter it and render firstly filter it filter it and store and remove all
the tickets and render filtered tickets now you have to write only this filter function
now the filter function will apply on this ticket array task info object and also you
can use task ID also this seems to be easy enough when you go and see from our project
perspective if you want to go and implement this search on straightforward even you can
find each piece of code already in our that script file you have to just pick it right
things and build it if I have to build it it will take me 15 minutes hardly I can build it
but what I want where the logic part you will be able to do it in half an hour 30 minutes but
where I am trying to push you guys is that I made design changes now you think of it how would you
accommodate search bar and how would you allow user to do it and how you make it better experience
build experience now as a product developer or engineer you also have to think right how
can you improve your existing application so I hope the problem statement is clear like what
yeah maybe under the Kanban board or anything if you want to reduce this font and give it you have
to think go and research the existing thing you go and check myntra flipkart Amazon or whatever
they have how how you can do it okay so just think of it that way or you want to add a toggle
button which will toggle between this filters and a search bar like anything that you want or else
you want to give it a create and delete button as a different thing it's up to you anything that
you can do but it's it's your choice so I want some innovation from your side also spend some
time this will push you to you know rewatch this whole code go through this code and then come back
so guys if you allow me 10 minutes we'll end the class for today can we go ahead and deploy this
application okay let's let's do this guys let's do this so for deployment also right this is a
static website isn't it when I say static website when I say static website what I exactly means
is that there is no specific interaction with real-time server okay only it has three things
html css js with no api calls being triggered okay so this static website you can always
you know there are a few set of deployments that you can use for static website so have anyone
explored something like github pages have anyone heard github pages
okay let me show you github pages
if I have I think I have one two projects guys I can show you
let me see if I have it give me a second guys I will go through my repository and see
so I'll show you this thing firstly let's say github also provides an ability to deploy your app
okay it's pretty straightforward like you can what whenever you create a repository right you
can go to repository once you create it okay then once you have updated it you can go to repository
create it give me a second they haven't provided everything here
okay terminal
okay they are showing through github let's say if I do this do this do this
okay let me see if I have any websites that I deployed I remember I have deployed but I
have to recheck it I've done some time back
this was something that I deployed when I was learning react long time back
okay like this is again you know add a meetup if you want to add a new meetup like you can
add something dummy data uh let's say www.google.com
okay I gave the right url now let's say image url uh images
okay yeah so this was one of the website but this is not the thing oh let me recheck if I have
yeah maybe this one
okay this is an empty repository but so I'll share you guys like how you can leverage github
pages okay but if you see this this is something that I deployed on worcel now worcel is actually
built by uh next.js team uh same team who built uh firstly react okay you can deploy your
applications here also like just if you click on start deploy okay once you connect with your
github repo once I authorize this one
okay now uh let's say I import this one
uh let's say I import this one
and it keeps me directly deploy button I don't need this way but
this is something that I deployed earlier so if you see this is the same website
but inside github pages also have deployed things I just want to know where did I do this
hmm anyways I'll come back to that one guys how did I do it on github pages github pages
is really simple you can do it directly on github you don't need any other website
uh you it's it's straightforward completely
I'll show you that one anyway straight one okay fine
but something that we are going to use today is netlify
okay have you heard of this one netlify earlier
so I was talking about three things right as of now if you see github pages
then you have let's say worcel and netlify these are really commonly used because for
static websites they allow you to freely deploy applications okay if you want a
free deployment you can use most probably github pages that's a really easy one like
you can go through documentation it will be written inside git only when you try to create
a repository but when you go for netlify this is a third party uh you know application which is
used to host your websites so let's see how you can do it this is pretty simple it's a one-step
game like let's say if i go into netlify and log in let's see if i have logins
uh let's say i log in with github
and okay did i deploy any applications earlier
okay we'll anyways build this in future guys there's one more application that i deployed
for the last patch but now if you if you want to deploy any other new website right uh let's say
go to sites add new site deploy if i hear what i'll do is like i'll i'll select deploy manually
and what i'll do it is that i'll pull the code and paste the code here okay so how would i do
that i'll click the browse to upload okay i'll uh have to go to dev full stack manjan
uh projects part uh let's say kanban board once i do this here we have three files index html
script js and style.css let's say click on upload just upload okay if you see
okay automatically everything will be handled for us now okay uh let's see if you see here
uh the initialization building deploying clean up everything is skipped but you know everything
was deployed the code is uploaded into this one and if you go and click this one right or open
production deploy your application is actually deployed so i made this fonts really less i guess
i have to play around with this fonts by default my browser was zoomed at 250 but can anyone check
if this is url is working for you try to access this url if anyone is able to access this kanban board
okay so it starts that straightforward you can try to create your own task check this
check this like once you let's say what i can what you can do is that let's say i bookmark this
okay instead of scalar let's say i make it to bookmarks bar kanban board now if i want to do
play around with this one let's say i'll open the kanban board and then let's say task one is to
complete assignments let's say i want to make it this one to be done uh assignments
okay and click options now once you do this let's say to be done maybe in progress then validate
once it is done you can do can complete and also you can delete that as whatever you want
okay this is something that i'm doing on production base so this is one of the way that
you can deploy it it's really simple when you can we add custom we can do that we can do that
we can do that uh let me explore this one i go to deploy settings
uh
okay configure
not this one pretty let's say this documentation
uh this doesn't allow us custom uh url
so
okay this is a site id that i got change the site name if you see
uh let's say this is a site name i can say kanban board
uh let's say it is it i say uttam uh i save it now once i did this i updated this as a site name
and site id will be consistent let's say if i go back to site overview
and i try to open this now so if you see i made this custom url upendra
so if you see i made this custom url upendra so just go into settings uh you will be able to update
it how the way you want to do it okay not a big deal so there's one more thing that if you want
to redeploy right uh let's say you go and uh let's say now that's fine uh let's say even if
we can do the lighthouse testing for this one plug in
uh okay key kanban board as i wrote kan board okay fine anyways
you can anyways i'll go back and update i'll show you back again how can how we can do this site
configuration uh change site name i say instead of this kanban board
let's say kanban board scale be appropriate okay now the site will be updated as this one
okay fine anyways like if you see uh for each one right now i'll have one question to you
just think of it like if it's if it is clicking to you now i have something like kanban board
and also i have something like local application which is running now i have this ticket one got
created here and for kanban board if you see tickets are not there here
why do you think it's not there for why it is this particular
thing is having like even if i refresh task on this day though if you see go and explore in the
application local storage i'm having this task if i go to kanban board
if i go to application in the local storage i don't have it
no why do you think this is how it is behaving it's so we earlier when i taught you this one
like having of 10 mb uh size so that 10 mb size is per one site you can have 10 sites
have 10 sites loading in a browser so each site can have 10 mb of data that can store in the
local storage that's the reason why when you keep on adding more and more websites right more and
more tabs the more amount of data that browser need to handle and the more amount of passing more
amount of things that are happening at long time if you see if you have 10 15 websites you can see
amount of the cpu consumption that is done by actually browser it's that makes really you know
slow your application your all sites are slow if you've just seen that in the earlier class
i had many websites open parallely for me okay so that's the reason why some it's it's not
suggestible that you know you do it that way sometimes you have a strong application which
is using more amount of memory from your let's say 32 gb 64 gb rams then it works fine but it
is supposed to try to use as many like let's say eight nine tabs not more than that
but i hope you got this point that you know the 10 mb size is not per a website not for the
particular key but it is for different all websites will have its own 10 mb and 5 mb
and 4 kb of data that point is clear right
uh guys so did you guys enjoy kanban board completely we have spent more than eight to nine
hours so do let me know if you have any doubts or any things that you want to share with me okay
but as of now i would say that this development part for kanban board from my side is completed
this development part for kanban board from my side is completed i hope someone goes and
implement that search filter and make some design changes and share it with me if it is something
that you can add on that i'll go and teach that subsequent batches also that this is done by a
previous batch some student then i'll name you there then we can bring it back okay someone
else will add on more future features then someone else will do right so i want to make
this as a proactive development task okay so guys if this is clear i would like to end the
session today here itself i'll start the doubt session uh you have enough time i would say that
have you know enjoy the weekend take rest uh get back with new energy where we'll learn
machine coding from the next session that's going to be further interesting things guys
please join me back in the tuesday's class okay so let me start the doubt session
okay
guys i have started the doubt session now anyone having any doubts they can post their doubts
uh and we can discuss this further uh if everything is clear feel free to drop uh and
can we go forget okay uh let me do one thing guys i'll share one website
i'm not sure guys like why they are not adding it i'll flag this one
um
okay
okay i'll i'll try to teach you basics of gits that i do in day to day okay now let's have since
we have some time now okay let's do this i'll take 10 15 minutes of kit class also i'll teach
you whatever i know okay so
how many of you understand something called remote repository
and local repository
okay
can we add domain name like uh canbatboard.com uh no that won't be possible up in there
because you have to buy that canbanboard.com uh domain only then you could be able to do
because for domain names you have to buy it yeah i'll share that can but uh canbanboard link
uh let's say i also started i thought someone will ask okay this test uh this is still working
but let me go to netlify and share the exact sites
so
i'll pin this kabir zoom it to 250 percent you can refix this one you know
the sizes of things like i i'll fix it up later but you can fix it up okay so coming back to this
one guys how many of you know understand this something called remote and local repository
does anyone understand this local and remote repository
no right so remote repository something which is present on your github
okay local repository something present on your machine
both can be pointing to same thing let's say if in our case fullstack jan batch fullstack jan
okay this is the github repository let's say we have this is this is on github now as soon as you
make any changes in everyday code whenever i'm making any changes or adding changes so i'm making
changes so i'm making changes in my local repository every time after my class i'm trying
to push something onto my report remote repository right so if you go and see if i show you something
in my here let's say i write down git remote okay if you see origin uh get a remote
okay so if you see there are a list of things if you see that what what it is showing like you can
add n number of things like git remote you can add a new urls set url okay remove the urls also
whatever things you have you can play around with this on you where you want to push this code now
when i say origin when it says origin now if you go and see in the github right let's say if i go
on open the github account uh this was a batch right now this main branch is something like
acting as my origin now if you see this is a particular uh link where i'm trying to push code
this https code right in general i'm interacting with this one okay this is the url which can be
helpful to clone it and this is the remote url where i'll be pushing my code using the local
repository this point is clear what is remote and local and whenever you are making changes
you are making it local you have to push them into remote repository so that changes can be
added here okay so this is just a theory as of now now so here whenever you do git remote
in local you will be able to see what is the
uh like remote repository url you will be able to see that okay or here we got an origin because
we are using only one branch as of now if you have multiple folks you will be able to see
uh exact url but now whenever i'm making changes okay now in order to push the code to here right
it goes through certain steps firstly all the changes that you do let's say if i show you the
changes that i do let's say i make some changes as a uh add something here extra string
okay now i am adding an extra string here and i save this if you see here in the vs code i can
see that there are changes now when i click plus there is something you can see as a staged
staged changes staged changes this one now let's say here i clear
git status if you see when i do git status
here if you see this changes to be committed changes to be committed if something is in green
whenever you use git commit this whatever in green color there that will be pushed
that is going to be pushed with this origin main why origin origin is some remote repository
as i've shown you remote repository url and it will be pushed to this particular branch called as main
now whenever you are doing this now let's say if i do this minus again i've added into changes now
let's see what is happening now if you see changes are not staged so it says that red in
color if you want to uh like you know add if you want to commit these changes you have to move this
to stage so what happens is whenever you are making any changes in your local right whenever
you are making changes you have to add them into called something called the staging area
staging area you can do it using git add file name
or git add dot when you do dot
dot
whenever you do dot you are adding all the files once you are added onto staging area then
you would be able to commit that code now whenever you want to commit it if you see here
it is also suggesting the command like it's it also keeps the suggestions like you can say git
add git commit so one of the best ways right if you stuck anywhere in the kit you can do something
like git help it will give you all the definitions like uh branch details commit merge rebase switch
tag you know fetch pull push now i'll come to what is like fetch full pull and push okay now
let's say if i want to push this change let's say i don't want to push this change but i'll
add some change let's say i say that i want to push something called as colors array i'm
adding this comment and i want to push this now once if you see in my change i'm adding colors
array i have added let's say i remove this now if you see if i do again git status
it is not added into staging area changes are not staged for the commit once i click git add
dot and i do git status again if you see changes are to be committed do you see the
difference between these two things once you make changes you have to move something from
changes to staging area is this point clear okay once we make this then we have to commit the code
let's say if i when i'm committing it what do i mean i'm saying that hey this is store this as
a one of the memory like like with one number like key value pairs only a key with a multiple
files memory now let's say i say that hey comments added no when i go and add it now if you see while
one file change changes got done and one insertion happened now this insertion happened inside this
particular commit inside the main branch but now this commit is still is in local repository
okay then once staging is done git commit
once you committed the code still it is in local repository you are supposed to move these changes
from here to here and you can do this using push the changes to origin so if you see many people
write down git push origin you sometimes when you are directly pointing to origin you need not to
give origin also so if you see if i do git push see that data got written and it is being pushed
into this particular url let me open this url okay now if i go into commits i have committed 34
comments now if you see in the comments commit this was a commit code if you see just now
that we will be able to use the information and everything what we have added
so i hope till now we are able to understand what is git commit git add git push what we are doing
what is local repository and remote repository right now imagine if someone else like you you
might not be alone working right on this git repo and let's say if someone else also added some
changes in your report repositories right let's say two people are working here on full stack chat
uh consider use case when i was teaching and shashut was teaching
right pardon with spelling both were teaching right earlier i was pushing code to remote
repository then shashut jumped in he taught you three classes he pushed code but in my local
repository do i have code what shashut has added into my repository as a collaborator
has added into my repository as a collaborator
by default do i have the code whatever he pushed
guys are you able to follow up i'm or i'm wasting my time like just want to know
like do i have the code what shashut has pushed maybe shashut would have added into this repository
if you go and see if i uh if you see uh intro to dom read me updated
event handling even dynamic dom right these codes were verified by me and he added this code yes
so this thing is present this changes whatever he have pushed into will be present in remote
repository but in local in my machine automatically code won't be downloaded which
is pushed by shashut i have to say can you give me all the information updated information in the
this remote repository when i say get pull i'm trying to pull from a particular branch
i'm updating my local repository on my machine i'm trying to fetch the updated now how can i do that
i can suggest say that git pull when i say git pull it says that already updated
okay let's let me show you something like how can you uh there's a difference how i'll show you
let's say now i go into read me and let me uh fetch some read me changes i'll fetch it from
past patch i'll update the read me let's say i go to read me file
now
this is rendering
let's say i try to push something called as canban board
uh how do i load this
anyways let's say we add something here if i want to edit this one
okay here let's say if i go and add it here okay now if you see it here what i'll do is i like have
to make changes let's say till can bad board one i've added here i missed for the last two classes
read me content let's say i go and update this one okay let's say i add for the next two classes
let's say class 15 and class 16
let's say it is i did this and let's say i commit changes here itself now i commit changes uh update
read me main branch okay now i don't need to push it because i committed changes directly
on remote repository oh hope that point is clear like how did i only with commit this was
100 right now if i go back to my local code do i have the recent commit that was made here
do i have that recent commit made there like can you see can board board 15 16
now if i want some changes which were done on the remote repository into my local let's say
if i want something to be pushed or pull the data whatever updates are done on the remote repository
if i want to get those data okay so if you see if you go into the collaborate section you will
see that it will that fetch and integrate if you when i say git pull it will fetch the data from
the top branch let's say i do git pull now once i do git pull let's see if you see read me file
got updated there are 13 new changes that were added now do you see this can man board can man
changes got added here automatically so do you understand how git pull and git push works
so whenever you are interacting with remote repository you have two things git push and
git pull is this clear so guys i believe i have covered some basics of it
then all the other things you can explore step by step is anyone able to follow up like
are you able to follow up right did you understand this a basics of git
i spent some 20 odd minutes on that okay
great guys
chalo then if this is clear how do you install git in vs code okay you don't need to install
git in vs code by default it will be there and someone was like if you see that if i open my
terminal let's say this is my terminal i have to show you if i have git installed here
git hyphen hyphen version if you say 2.3.81 or 2381 same will be here also git hyphen hyphen
version same version will be there so once you install on your like on your level of your
system that will be auto installed in your git this one also terminal okay kabir have some
small talk can we make task flag equal to false in the model event listener because
while creating a critic paper is an alt key should uh
okay sure we can do that
okay can we make uh yeah we have to install in the system some bit
model event listener
here right
now
it was add or remove
just let me check that keyword because we have two things add and remove
so
this one you want me to update right add task flag kavi
just rechecking with you
so
okay going back to while doing a model container
model container
no this will reset it let's say i launch this
no when i create it
it okay this is breaking then all the time
okay did i make some error 152
okay fine this is working fine thanks kabir
no thank you so even if you want to set up the git right you can go github
uh tutorial i guess github tutorials you can go github docs
let's say you can explore documentation but download github
you can check here like how can you download how can you play around with this one okay
github installation and setup
guys any other things that you want to point or likely can we end the session today
so
you
so i don't see any other doubts guys so i'll end the session today here
so thank you for joining enjoy the your time thank you pendra hope you enjoyed the whole project
project can band board so you have some homework part to be done on this if you're not able to do
even then i can help you out building the search bar because it's straightforward as i've told you
try it out do let me know let's meet back on the tuesday's class where we'll do actual machine
coding rounds because web development can be learned through projects but in interviews
something that you would be tested on is like machine coding rounds okay so let's meet back
and explore them okay so take rest solve the assignment problems let's meet back guys
so thank you for attending tuesday's sessions i'm stopping screen share see you on tuesday guys
you
anyways
You